<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="treeland_keyboard_state_notify_unstable_v1">
    <copyright><![CDATA[
    SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2026 UnionTech Software Technology Co., Ltd.
    SPDX-License-Identifier: MIT
    ]]></copyright>

    <description summary="global keyboard state notification">
        This protocol allows privileged clients to subscribe to global keyboard
        state changes (e.g. Caps Lock, Num Lock).

        Clients create watcher objects through the manager global, each bound
        to a seat. The client then configures the watcher with set_modifiers to
        choose which modifiers to monitor, and set_flags to choose which event
        types (locked, unlocked, or both) to receive. Configuration changes are
        double-buffered and take effect atomically when the client sends apply.
        Both set_modifiers and set_flags can be called multiple times before
        apply; only the values from the most recent calls are committed. This
        allows changing the configuration at runtime without destroying and
        recreating the watcher. After apply, the compositor sends a
        current_state event for each watched modifier containing its
        current lock state, so the client can synchronize its initial
        state without waiting for the next physical key press. The
        compositor then sends
        state_changed events on the watcher whenever any of the watched
        modifiers changes lock state globally, regardless of which surface
        has keyboard focus.

        This protocol is observation-only. Keyboard state changes are never
        consumed or intercepted by this protocol.

        Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
        phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
        corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
        only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
    </description>

    <interface name="treeland_keyboard_state_notify_manager_v1" version="1">
        <description summary="global keyboard state notification manager">
            The treeland_keyboard_state_notify_manager_v1 interface is a
            singleton global object used to create watcher objects for monitoring
            keyboard state changes on a given seat.

            A client may create multiple watcher objects for the same seat if
            needed.
        </description>

        <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
            <description summary="destroy the keyboard state notify manager">
                Destroy this
                treeland_keyboard_state_notify_manager_v1 object.

                Existing watcher objects created through this interface are not
                destroyed automatically. Clients should destroy those objects
                before destroying the manager.
            </description>
        </request>

        <request name="get_keyboard_state_watcher">
            <description summary="create a keyboard state watcher object">
                Create a treeland_keyboard_state_watcher_v1 object for
                monitoring keyboard state changes on the given seat, or on
                all seats if seat is null.

                The watcher is created with no modifiers and no flags set by
                default. The client should use set_modifiers and set_flags on
                the watcher to configure what to monitor.

                Note:
                1. The treeland_keyboard_state_watcher_v1 object must be destroyed
                before the associated wl_seat is destroyed.
            </description>
            <arg name="id" type="new_id"
                 interface="treeland_keyboard_state_watcher_v1"/>
            <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" allow-null="true"
                 summary="seat to monitor keyboard state on, or null for all seats"/>
        </request>
    </interface>

    <interface name="treeland_keyboard_state_watcher_v1" version="1">
        <description summary="keyboard state watcher">
            The treeland_keyboard_state_watcher_v1 interface represents a
            subscription to keyboard state changes on a specific
            seat.

            This object is created via get_keyboard_state_watcher on the
            treeland_keyboard_state_notify_manager_v1 global. The client
            configures the watcher with set_modifiers to choose which modifiers
            to monitor and set_flags to choose which state transitions to
            receive. Both can be changed at runtime. Configuration changes are
            double-buffered: set_modifiers and set_flags only update the pending
            state, which is applied atomically when apply is called.

            The compositor sends a current_state event for each modifier in
            the committed modifier set immediately after apply is called.
            It then sends
            state_changed events whenever any of the watched modifiers
            changes lock state, according to the committed modifiers and
            flags.
        </description>

        <enum name="modifier" bitfield="true">
            <description summary="keyboard modifier type">
                Bitfield of keyboard modifiers whose lock state can be
                monitored. Multiple modifier values can be combined using
                bitwise OR.

                caps_lock: the Caps Lock modifier.
                num_lock: the Num Lock modifier.
                scroll_lock: the Scroll Lock modifier.

                Examples:
                caps_lock: monitor only Caps Lock.
                caps_lock | num_lock: monitor both Caps Lock and Num Lock.
            </description>
            <entry name="caps_lock" value="1"
                   summary="Caps Lock modifier"/>
            <entry name="num_lock" value="2"
                   summary="Num Lock modifier"/>
        </enum>

        <enum name="watch_flag" bitfield="true">
            <description summary="modifier state transition flags">
                Flags to specify which modifier lock state transitions the
                client wants to be notified about.

                none: do not notify on any state transition.
                locked: notify when a watched modifier becomes locked.
                unlocked: notify when a watched modifier becomes unlocked.

                Examples:
                locked: the client receives events only when a modifier is
                locked.
                unlocked: the client receives events only when a modifier is
                unlocked.
                locked | unlocked: the client receives events on both.
            </description>
            <entry name="locked" value="1"
                   summary="notify when modifier is locked"/>
            <entry name="unlocked" value="2"
                   summary="notify when modifier is unlocked"/>
        </enum>

        <enum name="modifier_state">
            <description summary="modifier lock state">
                The current lock state of a keyboard modifier.
            </description>
            <entry name="unlocked" value="0"
                   summary="modifier is now unlocked"/>
            <entry name="locked" value="1"
                   summary="modifier is now locked"/>
        </enum>

        <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
            <description summary="destroy the keyboard state watcher">
                Destroy this treeland_keyboard_state_watcher_v1 object and
                stop receiving keyboard state notifications.
            </description>
        </request>

        <request name="set_modifiers">
            <description summary="set the modifiers to watch">
                Set the keyboard modifiers to watch on this watcher.

                The modifiers argument is a bitfield of values from the modifier
                enum (e.g. caps_lock = 1, num_lock = 2, scroll_lock = 4).
                Multiple modifiers can be combined using bitwise OR.

                Calling set_modifiers replaces any previously pending modifiers.

                This request only updates the pending configuration. The change
                takes effect when apply is called. If set_modifiers is called
                multiple times before apply, only the values from the most
                recent call are used.
            </description>
            <arg name="modifiers" type="uint" enum="modifier"
                 summary="bitfield of modifier enum values to watch"/>
        </request>

        <request name="set_flags">
            <description summary="change which state transitions to notify about">
                Change the watch flags for this watcher, selecting which modifier
                state transitions (locked, unlocked, or both) the client wants
                to be notified about.

                This request only updates the pending configuration. The change
                takes effect when apply is called. If set_flags is called
                multiple times before apply, only the values from the most
                recent call are used.
            </description>
            <arg name="flags" type="uint" enum="watch_flag"
                 summary="new watch flags"/>
        </request>

        <request name="apply">
            <description summary="apply pending configuration changes">
                Apply the pending configuration state for this watcher
                atomically.

                The compositor will use the modifiers and flags set by the most
                recent set_modifiers and set_flags calls as the new active
                configuration for this watcher. If set_modifiers or set_flags
                have not been called since the last apply (or since the watcher
                was created), the corresponding pending values remain unchanged.

                After this request, the pending configuration is considered
                consumed. Subsequent calls to set_modifiers or set_flags will
                begin a new pending configuration.

                The compositor will send a current_state event for each
                modifier in the newly committed modifier set immediately
                after processing this request.
            </description>
        </request>

        <event name="current_state">
            <description summary="current state of a watched modifier">
                Sent for each modifier in the committed modifier set after
                each apply call to provide its current lock state. For
                example, if the client watches caps_lock and num_lock, the
                compositor will send two current_state events, one for each
                modifier.

                This event is emitted before any subsequent state_changed
                events for the new configuration. It may be sent again
                after future apply calls if the client reconfigures the
                watcher.
            </description>
            <arg name="modifier" type="uint" enum="modifier"
                 summary="the modifier whose lock state is being reported"/>
            <arg name="state" type="uint" enum="modifier_state"
                 summary="the current lock state of the modifier"/>
        </event>

        <event name="state_changed">
            <description summary="a watched modifier has changed state">
                This event is sent when one of the watched modifiers changes
                lock state globally, according to the modifiers and flags
                currently set on this watcher.

                The modifier argument identifies which modifier changed state.
                The state argument indicates whether the modifier is now locked
                or unlocked.
            </description>
            <arg name="modifier" type="uint" enum="modifier"
                 summary="the modifier that changed lock state"/>
            <arg name="state" type="uint" enum="modifier_state"
                 summary="the new lock state of the modifier"/>
        </event>
    </interface>
</protocol>
